Guide to the Skidmore, Owings & Merrill: Michael McCarthy records, 1970-1998.
Skidmore, Owings & Merrill: Michael McCarthy records
- Series VII. Architectural Projects, Commissions, and Built Works, 1964-1998 (SOM Years)
  - Mangaf Resort Hotel - Presbyterian Hospital of New York
    - Methodist Hospital Medical Pavilion, Brooklyn, New York, 1992–1997
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 44)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
      - Personnel list, photocopies of perspective renderings, and published articles, Undated (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - National Commercial Bank of Saudi Arabia, Jeddah, Saudi Arabia
      Architectural, engineering, and interior design services for financial institution and office building located in Jeddah’s new commercial center between the old city and the Red Sea.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 44)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
      - Promotional brochure on Saudi Arabia, Undated (Box 33)
      - Project fact sheet, personnel list, published articles, Arthur Drexler, Three New Skyscrapers (New York: MoMA, 1983), 1983 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - National Commercial Bank of Saudi Arabia, Park Avenue, New York, New York, 1982-1983
      1993-1994 Renovations
      1983 Interior design for a branch bank, including executive office interiors, trading room, conference room, open office space, and lunchroom
      1989 Study to re-plan existing space to add new offices and staff work stations
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 44)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
      - Published articles, Undated (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - New York Public Library for the Performing Arts (NYPL Library and Museum of the Performing Arts, Lincoln Center Library), New York, New York
      1965 Original structure completed
      - Proposals and final report, September 1991 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - New York Stock Exchange, Bond Room and Options Trading Floor, 20 Broad Street, New York, 1979
      - Slides, Undated (Box 50)
      - Existing facilities study (8/20/79) and other reports and published articles, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Park Avenue Plaza, Park Avenue between 52nd and 53rd Streets, New York, 1977–1981
      Architectural design of a 44-story office tower and interior design of lobby and retail arcade. Development included an interior plaza.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 44)
      - Project summary, fact sheet, specifications, and published article, Undated (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Petron Megaplaza, Manila, Philippines, 1994-1997
      - Design and working drawings (Box 89, 90)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 44)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
    - Pratt Institute, Leo J. Pantas Residential Center, Brooklyn, New York, 1984–1988
      1987 Master plan for the Institute’s development to the year 2000 to accommodate 2,000 resident students. Leo J. Pantas Residential Center, consisting of two perpendicular wings of eight and six stories in an L-shape, connected by a clock tower containing the elevators and main lobby. A gatehouse was designed, but not built. Prefabricated modular housing units for 220 students built as an interim measure
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 44)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Master plan narrative (1/91), correspondence, dedication, invitation, project summary, awards application, and newspaper clippings, 1991 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Presbyterian Hospital in the City of New York (Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center), New York, 1981–1990
      1981 Master Plan
      The documentation for Presbyterian Hospital covers the complex generally and also includes material for the 1981 master plan for a multi-phase modernization of this teaching hospital and for these specific projects: Allen Pavilion (Community Hospital), Center for Women and Children, Milstein Pavilion, and the Energy Court Galleria, interconnecting bridges and tunnels, addition to the service building, and renovations as detailed in the following entries.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 44)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Project summary, bibliography, published articles, and newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Presbyterian Hospital in the City of New York (Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center), Allen Pavilion (Community Hospital), New York, 1982-1988
      A 300-bed facility with ancillary diagnostic and treatment areas. Built on a part of Baker’s Field donated by Columbia University.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 44)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Project summary and published articles, Undated (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Presbyterian Hospital in the City of New York (Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center), Center for Women and Children, New York, 1988
      An expansion of the diagnostic and treatment facilities completed in 1988.
      - Project summary, Undated (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Presbyterian Hospital in the City of New York (Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center), Milstein Pavilion, New York, 1990
      A 745-bed facility with ancillary diagnostic and treatment areas completed in 1990. May be identified in some documentation as “Mainframe.”
      - Working drawings for “Mainframe: Phase B” Wall sections, Electrical vaults, Tunnels and Basements, Riverside drive base details, Performance criteria, Exterior details, Entrances, Bridges, Penthouse details, Skylight details, Exterior details, Reflected ceiling plans, Undated (Box 73a)
      - Working drawings for “Mainframe: Phase B” Reflected ceiling plans, Ceiling details, Lighting fixture details, Color finish plans, Undated (Box 73b)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 44)
      - Awards application, published articles, and newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 27, Folder 10)
      - American Institute of Architects New York Chapter 1993 Design Award, Special Recognition for Health Care Facilities, 1993 (Box 33)
    - Presbyterian Hospital in the City of New York (Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center), Energy Court Galleria, New York, 1981-1990
      Interconnecting bridges and tunnels, addition to the service building, and renovations. Not built.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 44)
      - Project summary, Undated (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Ras Abu Soma, Egypt - Staten Island Hospital projects
    - Ras Abu Soma, Hurghada, Egypt, 1989-1990
      Master plan and architecture for vacation resort occupying the Abu Soma Peninsula. Phased village developments featuring a marina, hotels, casinos, and private villas linked by open spaces
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 45)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Brochure, Undated (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Rashid Hospital Dubai, United Arab Emirates, 1996
      Design for hospital and emergency center including an ICU, medical and trauma wings, surgery center, short stay ward, and helipad.
      Competition only.
      - Design drawings (Box 59)
    - Rizal Commercial Banking Corporation (RCBC) Office Building, Ayala Avenue, Manila, Philippines, 1995-1997
      The RCBC Project includes development of a full block in the Makati section of Manila. Two towers rest on a two-story common podium containing branch banks, restaurants, a food court, retail facilities, health club, and 500-seat auditorium. The owner’s tower overlooks a “garden in the sky.” The project also includes a museum, theater, and “Galleria.”
      - Drawings - Reduced copies of design development drawings, Elevations, Sections, Catwalk level plan (Box 72, 91)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 45)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Personnel list, correspondence, prospectus, and photocopies of construction photographs, April 28, 1999 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Saint Luke’s/Roosevelt Hospital Center, West 114th Street (Saint Luke’s site),Tenth Avenue (Roosevelt site) New York, 1986–1994
      1986 Master plan for Certificate of Need
      1991 Renovation and new 13-story facility on Roosevelt site. Renovation and new nine-story building on St. Luke’s site
      Zion and Breen were the landscape architects.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 45)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Personnel list, “New Building Guide,” published articles, and newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Schering Realty Corporation, Office Building K-6, Kenilworth, New Jersey, 1980–1983
      Expansion
      SOM Project #3560
      - Working drawings (Box 92)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 45)
      - Published articles, Undated (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Shalila Residential Project (H. E. Sheik Nahyan bin Mubarak al-Nahyan Residential Building), Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates, 1996
      Luxury residential complex featuring apartments having both exterior views and interior views of an enclosed tropical garden of exotic plants, streams, and waterfalls.
      Three schemes were presented to the client.
      - Correspondence and newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 27, Folder 15)
      - Prospectus including reduced copies of drawings, Undated (Box 33)
    - Shaw-Walker Company Muskegon, Michigan, 1975-1977
      Design of an open-plan furniture system to be manufactured and sold as a standard product.
      - Furniture catalog and photographs of existing furniture, Undated (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Shell Oil Company (One Shell Plaza),Houston, Texas, 1972
      Bruce Graham, design partner, Chicago office
      1990-1994 Renovations
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 45)
      - Design proposals and newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Shell Oil Company (Two Shell Plaza),Houston, Texas, 1972
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 45)
      - Design proposals and newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Shell Oil Company Refinery Delaware, 1970
      Roy O Allen, design partner
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Published articles regarding environmental concerns, Undated (Box 27, Folder 18)
    - Silver Brook Corporate Center (Cigna North Campus) Bloomfield, Connecticut, 1989-1990
      Master plan and concept design for mixed-use complex including corporate headquarters building, investment office space, hotel, retail, and residential components.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 45)
      - Slides (also includes images of Connecticut General and Emhart, other built works on or near this site), Undated (Box 51)
      - Project summary, advertising brochure, and published articles, Undated (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - Southtrust Tower, Birmingham, Alabama, 1984-1986
      Boston office
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
    - Staten Island Hospital, Staten Island, New York, 1988-1990
      Master plan for a new addition and phased renovation to accommodate expanded services.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 45)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Project summary and awards application, Undated (Box 27, Folder 20)
  - TampaSphere - World Centre projects
    - TampaSphere, Tampa, Florida, 1981-1984 and 1986
      Two schemes for an office, retail, commercial. and hotel complex including parking facilities.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 45)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Project summary and brochures, Undated (Box 27, Folder 21)
    - Texaco Headquarters, Harrison, New York, 1973-1977
      1980-1981 Expansion study
      1988-1992 Interior renovations
      Collection materials describe three commissions: original three-story suburban headquarters facility and interiors; expansion studies; and interior renovation of headquarters facility.
      - Working drawings, Undated (Box 93a, 93b, 93c)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 45)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Project summary, design program, space analysis, awards application, published articles, and newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 27, Folder 22)
      - 1977 Award of Merit for Texaco Harrison Office Facility “in recognition of the imaginative and skillful use of cast-in-place and precast pre-stressed concrete to achieve aesthetic expression, function and economy in a major company headquarters building”; testimonial of appreciation from Alfred C. De Crane, Jr., Chairman of the Board of Texaco, to the Texaco Harrison Office Building Renovation Team, May 21, 1992, May 21, 1992 (Box 31)
      - Texaco 75th anniversary memorabilia, Undated (Box 38)
    - Tinton Falls Development, Tinton Falls, New Jersey, 1988
      Master plan for phased commercial development on a 52-acre site planned in cooperation with a landscape artist.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 45)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
    - Transitional Housing for the Homeless, Greater New York City area, 1988-1995
      SOM Project #6121
      Eleven housing units constructed for singles and families at various locations throughout the four boroughs. The project as a whole received the Distinguished Architecture Award Citation from the New York Chapter of the American Institute of Architects in 1992. SWA Group were the landscape architects
      - Working drawings - 1150 Commonwealth Avenue, Bronx, Undated (Mapcase-folder 3)
      - Working drawings - 1150 Commonwealth Avenue, Bronx, Undated (Mapcase-folder 4)
      - Working drawings - 1150 Commonwealth Avenue, Bronx, Undated (Mapcase-folder 5)
      - Working drawings - 1150 Commonwealth Avenue, Bronx, Undated (Mapcase-folder 6)
      - Working drawings - 22 East 118-119th Street, Manhattan, Undated (Mapcase-folder 7)
      - Working drawings - 1381 East New York Avenue, Brooklyn, Undated (Mapcase-folder 8)
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 45)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Project summary, awards applications, list of NYC personnel involved in the project, list of contractors, published articles, and newspaper clippings, Undated (Box 27, Folder 23-25)
      - Art Commission of the City of New York, Award for Excellence in Design, 1988 (Box 31)
      - American Institute of Architects, New York Chapter, Distinguished Architecture Citation, 1992 (Box 31)
      - American Institute of Architects, New York Chapter, Andrew J. Thomas Pioneer in Housing Award; New York State Association of Architects Citation for Design, 1993 (Box 33)
    - United Arab Emirates Chancery, Washington, D.C., 1993–1994
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 46)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Notes for presentation, February 1st, 1994 (Box 27, Folder 26)
    - United States Air Force Academy, Aviation Leadership Museum, Colorado Springs, Colorado, 1956-1962
      Chicago office
      1991-1992 Proposed renovation and addition
      - Photocopies of area comparisons and schematic drawings, Undated (Box 27, Folder 27)
    - Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Cowgill Hall Addition, Blacksburg, Virginia, 1993-1994
      - Design drawings and studies, Undated (Box 33)
      - Shop drawings, Undated (Box 33)
      - Schematic design report (December 16th, 1993), meeting minutes and correspondence, December 16th, 1993 (Box 27, Folder 28)
    - Westchester Corporate Office Park, Yonkers, New York, 1987-1988
      Phase I: Office tower, with retail space and parking; Phase II: Hotel; Phases III and IV: Offices.
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 46)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Project summary, Undated (Box 27, Folder 29)
    - World Centre, Manila, Philippines, 1992–1996
      Included are offices, telecommunications facilities, health club, cafeteria, retail, parking garage, and helipad
      - Photographs, Undated (Box 46)
      - Slides, Undated (Box 51)
      - Project fact sheet, summary, and award application, Undated (Box 27, Folder 30)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Catalogued individually in the Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections
Architecture of Skidmore, Owings & Merrill, 1950-1962 (New York: Praeger, 1963)
CU call number: NA737.S53 D19
Architecture of Skidmore, Owings & Merrill, 1963-1973( New York: Architectural Book Publishing Company, 1974), CU call number: NA737.S53 D77 1974
Skidmore, Owings & Merrill: Architecture and Urbanism, 1973–1983 (Stuttgart: Verlag Gerd Hatje; NY: Van Nostrand Reinhold, 1983), CU call number: NA737.S53 B974
Skidmore, Owings & Merrill: Selected and Current Works, 1984–1994 (Master Architect Series) (Mulgrave, Victoria, Australia, 1995), CU call number: NA737.S53 S54 1995
Skidmore, Owings & Merrill (s.l., s.n., 1976), CU call number:
Art at Work: The Chase Manhattan Collection (NY: E. P. Dutton, 1984), CU call number: N6512 .A77
Marjory Jacobson, Art for Work: The New Renaissance in Corporate Collecting (Boston: Harvard Business School Press, 1993), CU call number: N5206 .J23x 1993
The Chase Art Program: A Strategy for the 1990’s (1993), CU call number:
Art at Work: Forty Years of the Chase Manhattan Collection (New York: Chase Manhattan Corp., 2000), CU call number: Fine Arts Library (Rand Hall) N5207.5.C5 A4x 2000; Kroch Library Rare & Manuscripts (Non-Circulating) Rare Books N6512 .A77 2000 ++
Joseph Rosa, Albert Frey, Architect (NY: Rizzoli, 1990), CU call number: NA737.F89 R78
Renata Holod and Hasan-Uddin Khan, Contemporary Mosque: Architects, Clients and Designs since the 1950s (New York: Rizzoli, 1997), CU call number: NA4670 .H65 1997